[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have a few questions that usually come up in regard to one of your essays, or one of the talks we did in the past, called the Taming that Sensual Itch.
[SPEAKER_01]: And one of the common questions is, isn't there a danger of intensifying craving by not giving in to the sensual itch of the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: If one doesn't relieve the body's sexual tension, won't it increase and spill over into more unwholesome behaviors?
[SPEAKER_00]: We will certainly increase initially the pressure
[SPEAKER_00]: But whether it spills over or not, that means... depends on whether you act out of it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it cannot automatically spill over, unless you spill it over.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the responsibility never really leaves you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point where it matters, is the point of your choice and your action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, of course, saying no to an unrestrained habit,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna amplify the habit initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no danger in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is in you perpetually acting out of habit.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's this assumption that if you repress your desires, you know, you are going to... that repression will lead you to automatically do bad things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not how things work.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that probably came from some
[SPEAKER_00]: school of psychology, or some theory, at some point, the repression, we mustn't repress, but I'm pretty sure that there are plenty of schools, even within the worldly psychology, they would refute and dispute that as a factual truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't matter how much the pressure builds up, it cannot make you act unless you choose to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, people that resort to the view of, oh, repression is bad, it will make me act automatically, are the people that hold a view that they're not responsible to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, saying no to yourself, especially if you haven't been doing it, will hurt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly like withdrawing from the drugs would, or any other addiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it still can't make the drugs come to you on its own,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or any addictive substance, unless you choose to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you undermine your own decision to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you need to repress things in order to pressurize them sufficiently enough, in order to contain them, in order to see the line where your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And once that's clarified, that's how the mind grows.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind grows out of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is no pressure of restraint, there is no growth of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything you do about it is just on the level of wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any practices you might be doing, any meditation you might be doing, if it's not done, on the basis of seeing the danger in the slightest fault and sense restraint, is just wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just fantasy world you're building up.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is not growing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is just becoming more equipped how to manage and avoid its own responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manage suffering and avoid responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if, on the other hand, the mind is pressured, or pressurized, through sensory strain, through seeing the danger in the slightest fault, through withdrawal from sensuality, even if you don't think about developing your mind further and growing it, you will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the pressure makes you do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, you don't take all the pressure
[SPEAKER_00]: All at once.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or expect to be able to hold it all overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you have a view that pressure is bad because I might choose to do things and it's not really my fault, it's the pressure, then there is no development for you because of that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't hold that view, even if you keep failing to contain the pressure and to build it up, at least you're working towards it, because you're not neglecting the responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not justifying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, containing the mind, confining it, building up the pressure, helps it grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are discerning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Helps it grow, outlines it for you better, doesn't make it spill out through careless actions, which blurs the lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: Between the mental pressures and your own choices and your own fuel, eh... so everything just becomes one thing and you just sort of submit to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start, eh... building up the pressure through the right sense restraint, virtue, withdrawal from precepts, celibacy, it outlines the mind, it outlines the extent of that pressure that doesn't come from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, consequently, it outlines your own responsibility when you choose to give in or blur the lines yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see that I can choose to give in to this pressure, I can choose not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can choose not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already the growth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing that choice, it's already a form of growth.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the full extent, recognizing that choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the detachment that one should be aiming for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you detach yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: From your mind, when the mind is sufficiently pressurized and you haven't been acting out of it, that outlines it as a separate entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't have to be figuring out what cittanimitta is and what all these similes of taming the citta are.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be seeing it, because you separated it from yourself through pressurizing it correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: By making it stand out, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not acting out of the mind, it starts to stand out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It almost gets frustrated with... You see the boundary of frustration.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the boundary of the mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes out of its hiding, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You force it out, exactly.